if you recall when we looked at the
pre-socratic philosophers and we came to
the tension between Parmenides and
heraclitus
I mentioned that what happened
was that after the impasse between those
two giants in philosophy a period of
skepticism and this worldly-ism
came into that vacuum that threatened
the very fabric of civilization and how
that Socrates
stepped into that vacuum and sought to
restore sober sanity to theoretical
thought and I also mentioned in passing
that that
impasse sort of thing happens with the
kind of cyclical regularity in the
history of Western thought and I
mentioned it for this reason that I
happen to believe we're in one of those
periods right now a period of skepticism
and the degeneration of theoretical
thought well after the the real Titans
of the ancient world Plato and Aristotle
ended up in tension another period of
skepticism came into Vogue where
philosophers turned their attention away
from searching for ultimate truth
thinking that the Quest for metaphysics
was basically a Fool's errand and again
turned their attention to concrete
matters of this world and so we had a
Revival of skepticism among the Greeks
and along with that Revival of
skepticism we saw the emergence of the
two most important philosophies that
fall followed after Aristotle namely
stoicism and epicureanism and I'm not
going to treat those two philosophies
other than to say in passing that as
different as they were they shared a
common desire and that was to find the
secret of living the happy life
how to live and exp and gain what they
called philosophical atarakia or peace
of mind
and they're important for this reason
that they're the only schools of
philosophy that are explicitly mentioned
in the New Testament where when Paul
visited Athens the cultural centered of
the ancient world he encountered
representatives from the school of
stoicism and from the epicureans but the
really important movement
that came to pass during these days was
the origin of the Christian church
and the widespread domination of
Christian theology
in fact there are historians in fact
secular historians who've argued that in
the midst of this vacuum this second
cycle of pessimism and skepticism that
arose after Aristotle and Plato
that again civilization was threatened
and the only thing that saved it was the
Advent of Christianity which once again
brought attention to ultimate truth and
gave a sound intellectual basis for
understanding the world in which we live
and in this regard some have argued that
the most important philosopher between
Aristotle and say plotinus in the 3rd
Century A.D was the Apostle Paul
but we don't normally think of Paul as a
philosopher he was more engaged with
missionary activity as a preacher and as
an evangelist and as a theologian but in
any case between
the death of Aristotle and the beginning
of the third Century Christianity is
dominating the intellectual climate
and platonism has pretty much Fallen by
the wayside but it has by no means
become extinct
and in the third Century we see a kind
of rebirth or Renaissance of ancient
platonic thought
in a movement that was called
Neo
platonism
and as you know the prefix Neo means new
and what the
neo-platonists wanted to do was to
reconstruct ancient platonism but to
make certain changes and adaptations to
account for the impact of Christianity
some of the radical ideas that were
introduced by Christian thought into the
world of ideas were
first of all the idea of the absolute
singular person
now Aristotle had given us an absolute
singular concept with his idea of God as
the unmoved Mover but Christianity and
Judaism had brought into the Forefront
the idea of the ultimate solution
to the ancient questions of philosophy
of the searching for Ultimate Reality
The RK the chief truth
and the solution to the question of
motion and the solution of the question
of life were found in the concept of the
Christian judeo-christian concept of God
who is the absolute Eternal personal
creator
in whom we live and move and have our
being
now the idea of a creation
by a voluntary action
of an eternal being was something the
Greeks did not have in their philosophy
even with Aristotle Aristotle's idea of
God was a God who
eternally moves things
but does not create them out of nothing
now we'll explore that in more detail
pretty soon when we get to the thinking
of the great Saint Augustine but for now
let's just notice in passing that the
idea of the absolute singular and the
idea of the trinitarian concept of God
where radical Innovations to theoretical
thought because the Trinity now gives us
the idea of absolute Oneness with whom
within that Unity there is
eternal diversity so that the one in the
many come together in the Christian
concept of God thirdly the other notion
that became so vitally important to the
the future of theoretical thought was
the Christian
philosophy of History
the world is something that is created
by God
it has a beginning
and not only does it have a beginning
but it has a terminal point and that is
moving in the direction of a divinely
ordained blueprint
so that history
is not cyclical that just goes on and on
and on and on having no beginning and no
end
but history is part of the creation of
this absolute singular God
who not only starts things going like an
unmoved mover
but who maintains sovereignty over his
creation and over the events of History
in other words the concept of Divine
Providence
by which God is totally committed to
this world and this time was in many
ways a radical thought for the ancient
mind now it's against this background
that we see the entrance of neoplatonism
and there were many distinguished
thinkers who are under the category of
neoplate platonous but the founder of
this movement was a man by the name of
plotinus
and plotinus lived in the third Century
born around 203 died around
270.
now when platinus developed his form of
philosophy which is an attempt to to
restructure and reconstruct Plato
he did it as a conscious alternative to
Christianity
he was aware of the widespread influence
of Christian thought
he opposed Christian thought at the
intellectual level and saw it as
fallacious and had destroyed the the uh
the Brilliance of Plato's contribution
to the world and so he sought to come up
with a philosophical alternative to
Christianity now many of the features
that we find in his philosophy show
certain Stark
similarities to a movement that began
earlier that the Christian church had to
confront in its earliest days which was
the heresy of gnosticism which was a a
syncretistic religion that Blended
together all sorts of ideas from
Oriental dualism Persian mysticism
Greek philosophy and a little dab of
Christianity in it but we're going to
leave that aside for the sake of of time
in this and look more specifically at
platonism or neoplatonism
platinus did not reject rationality
but believe that the highest source of
knowledge was through mystical intuition
in fact the only real Avenue to ultimate
truth came through mystical experience
and there were very few people
who were gifted with mystical intuition
who were part of what we might call here
the mystical Elite now it's at this
point that we see one clear point of
contact with earlier gnosticism because
the gnostics repudiated the ordinary
ways of knowing through reason and sense
perception and believe that the only
true way of knowing god or or ultimate
truth was through some kind of direct
immediate intuition that only a few
gifted people had who were the gnosticoi
those who were quote in the know so we
see a similarity there between
gnosticism and platinus at this point
but for platinus the good life The
Virtuous life
is the life of the Mystic who makes a
pilgrimage a long life's way from being
preoccupied with the physical world
where most people spend their lives
just as materialists
their whole life is is focused on things
on things that you can handle taste
touch see and hear and that sort of
thing
and he said that the First Step Beyond
that is to the contemplative life
whereby the mind
rises above the shadowy cave of Plato
where people are locked into the world
of material things the world of the
receptacle remember Plato wanted us to
get out of the cave of sense perception
and in to the realm of the Mind where
contemplation is the highest sort source
of Truth
well
platinus adds a new dimension to this
that we there's still another stage
after that and it is the stage of
mystical Union
now
how does this fit with Christianity
you read the New Testament and they're
obvious
they're obviously elements of mysticism
found within it and Paul's up in the
third heaven and and Paul talks about
our Union with Christ or what we would
call the mystical Union of the believer
with Christ and so on
but there's a different kind of thinking
in historic Christian mysticism from
what we find in these ancient
philosophies
for the ancient Mystic
this stage of progression this movement
this pilgrimage that I've talked about
that begins with sense perception or
sensation
and then moves through contemplation
and then moves to what the mystics call
communio
which is
a being with
God a communion with God we talk in
Christian theology about the communion
of the Saints and the sense in which we
have fellowship with each other not only
with those who are alive but with those
who are part of the church past present
and future and so on
but that's
that's the end of the road for Christian
mysticism the highest form of mysticism
is to have this mystical communion with
God
but not so with plotinus and other
Mystics the next stage is a union
where you become one with God now this
is a common feature in Eastern religions
where the goal of your religious
experience is to lose your personal
identity
to become one with the oversoul and so
often you'll hear the illustration of
the drop of water that falls into the
ocean that loses its identity as it
becomes absorbed into the whole of
things
now this is significant for plotinus
because of his concept of God
for plotinus
God is called the one with a capital O
hen the one
where he calls God
he
one in such a way that would suggest
a pure pantheism
but most experts who study platinus say
that platinus was not really your garden
variety variety pantheism in fact he
tried to avoid pantheism
and at the same time avoid Christianity
but still the highest being is called
the one now here's the problem
you can't know the one
the one escapes all possible knowledge
of what it is or who it is
and the important introduction to
philosophy though he wasn't the first
one to do this actually but the emphasis
for plotinus was to introduce a way of
knowing which he called the Via
nagaziones
sometimes called the Via negativa but it
means the way of negation
by describing things and in this case
God
simply by saying what God is Not
now historic Christianity makes use of
this to some degree some of the things
that we say about God employ the way of
negation when we say for example that
God is infinite
or invisible
or immutable what are we saying
we're saying that he's not finite he's
not visible and that he's not mutable
we're just simply saying what he isn't
we are finite visible and mutable and at
this point when we use these words to
describe the attributes of God we're
saying this is a way in which God is
different from us he's not visible like
you were visible he's not mutable like
you were mutable he's not finite like
you were finer so we use the way of
negation
but that's not all we use but for now
let's see how it functions with uh with
platinus to give you a feel
for the thinking of plotinus
I'm going to read a somewhat lengthy
quote from his hand which is something I
don't normally do when I teach is read
quotations but this is this one I think
gives such a clear flavor of where
platinus was coming from that I think
you will enjoy it
he says this the intelligence
is a thing
and belongs to real being
the one or the capital O
is not anything
but prior to all things
neither is it a kind of real being
real being possesses a character
comparable to shape
the intelligible shape of the real
but the one is not shapen even by
intelligible shape
for that principle which generates all
thing all things cannot be anything of
them at all
it is not a thing it's not quality it's
not quantity it's not intelligence nor
Soul it does not move
and yet
it is not at rest
it is neither in space nor in time
it is the uniform absolute or rather the
form less
remember Aristotle called God pure form
of Tinus
God is formless
because he's prior to all form and prior
to motion and prior to rest for these
lasts are characters of real being
and make reality manifold if it be asked
why the one having no movement is not at
rest we answer because only a being
or only two a being must one or both of
these predicates apply
any being that we conceive of must
either be at rest or in motion
but if the one is not a being
then neither the categories of rest or
motion apply to it
a stationary object is at rest but it is
not rest and so also if the one be at
rest rest would be added to it as an
accident and it would no longer remain
simple
even to name it the cause is to
predicate an accident not of the one but
of ourselves it signifies that while the
one abides within itself we have nothing
derived from it he that would speak
exactly now listen must not name it by
this name or by that
we can but Circle as it were about its
circumference seeking to interpret it in
speech or in our experience now shooting
near the mark but again disappointed of
our aim by reason of the antinomies or
contradictions found within it
now you can't believe how many
philosophers and theologians since
platinists have employed this kind of
approach
to an understanding of God
in our day we think of Paul tillich
who's one of the most important
theologians of the 20th century
who said that God is not being he is the
ground of being
antilic I remember lecturing to students
on one occasion said that God is neither
personal nor impersonal but is the
ground of Personality now what he was
getting at is that personality
or impersonality can only be predicated
of beings
but if God's not a being but the ground
of being then these terms don't apply
and one student raise their hand and
said Dr tillich is the ground of
Personality personal or impersonal until
it got all exercised at him for saying
that I mean it's the same kind of way of
speaking that we're finding here in
plotinus and obviously the question one
has to ask
is what is the difference
between the one
who is not being or a being
and nothing
that's the real question
and I think that we have to come to the
conclusion that his God in the final
analysis
is nothing
but this God who is unknowable
emanates from his own Oneness
the different levels of reality that we
find in this world the reality of mind
the reality of Soul the reality of
matter another point of contact with the
world view of the early gnostics and the
farther away you get from the one and
the lowest level of emanations that
proceed from him
is matter or the physical which becomes
for platinus the principle of evil
and one of the most important
influences of plotinus in the history of
philosophy is the influence he had on
Saint Augustine
because Augustine was converted to
neoplatonism in his earlier years
and then when he became a Christian he
became the chief critic of the ancient
world of neoplatonism so we'll look at
him
in our next study